A Guide to the Papers of O. Henry from the Doubleday and Company Archive 1894 (1984-1927) 1958
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of O. Henry from the Doubleday and Company Archive, 1894 (1894-1927) 1958
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
7457
This collection consists of 62 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was given to the Library by Doubleday and Company through Raymond R. Ammarelle, Charlottesville, Virginia, on March 21, 1964.
Scope and Content Information
The collection contains manuscripts and typescripts of several short stories by O. Henry; radio adaptations of O. Henry stories by Henry Fisk Carlton, one in collaboration with Robert Winternitz; material regarding a film adaptation of "Best Seller" by Roy Mason; and an unpublished biographical account of Henry's Texas days by Paul Adams.
With these are a letter, 1908? July 16, Henry to Stephen Fiske thanking him for favorable reviews; correspondence, 1910, 1925, of Fiske and Mason with Doubleday and Co.; and a letter, 1958 June 20, of Kate Steichen regarding Doubleday's Henry collection with a bibliography of his work.
There are also three printed articles by Henry, and a published letter and pen-and-ink drawing by him.
Contents List
- Manuscripts
  - Cast of Characters of O. Henry's "Best Seller," adapted for film by Roy Mason 1925, TMs, 4 p.
    with autograph corrections
  - Continuity of Scenes for O. Henry's "Best Seller," adapted for film by Roy Mason 1925, TMs, 94 p.
  - Scene Plot of O. Henry's "Best Seller," adapted for film by Roy Mason 1925, TMs, 4 p.
  - Synopsis of O. Henry's "Best Seller," adapted for film by Roy Mason 1925, TMs, 17 p.
  - "Blind Man's Holiday," adapted for radio by Henry Fisk Carlton n.d., Near-Print, 32 p.
  - "The Brief Debut of Tildy," adapted for radio by Henry Fisk Carlton 1927 Sept 7, TMs (C), 37 p.
  - "A Cactus Thorn" by William Sydney Porter n.d., AMsS, 8 p.
    Last three pages supplied in typescript. Posthumously published as "The Cactus."
  - "A Chaparral Prince," adapted for radio by Henry Fisk Carlton n.d., Near-Print, 24 p.
  - "The Clarion Call," adapted for radio by Henry Fisk Carlton n.d., Near-Print, 26 p.
  - "Entertaining By Ear," by William Sydney Porter n.d., TMs, 2 p.
  - "The Ghost that Came to Old Angels," by William Sydney Porter n.d., AMsS, 13 p.
  - "The Hand that Riles the World," adapted for radio by Henry Fisk Carlton n.d., Near-Print, 37 p.
  - "The Handbook of Hymen," adapted for radio by Henry Fisk Carlton 1927 Sept 14, TMs (C), 34 p.
  - "How the Country Was Saved," by William Sydney Porter n.d., TMs, 3 copies, 1 p.
  - "If You See It in the ---- It's So," by William Sydney Porter n.d., TMs, 1 p.
  - "Jack, the Giant-Killer," by William Sydney Porter n.d., TMs, 4 p.
  - "Jeff Peters as a Personal Magnet," adapted for radio by Henry Fisk Carlton n.d., Near-Print, 31 p.
  - "Little Speck in Garnered Fruit," adapted for radio by Henry Fisk Carlton 1927 Oct 14, TMs (C), 27 p.
  - "Mammon and the Archer," adapted for radio by Henry Fisk Carlton 1927 Aug 10, TMs (C), 28 p.
  - "A New Candidate for Sympathy," by William Sydney Porter n.d., TMs, 2 p., 3 copies
  - "One Dollar's Worth," adapted for radio by Henry Fisk Carlton 1927 Sept 30, TMs (C), 32 p.
  - "Past One at Rooney's," adapted for radio by Henry Fisk Carlton and Robert Winternitz n.d., Near-Print, 36 p.
  - "Phoebe," adapted for radio by Henry Fisk Carlton n.d., Near-Print, 27 p.
  - "Pursuing Ideals," by William Sydney Porter n.d., TMs, 9 p.
  - "The Ransom of Mack," adapted for radio by Henry Fisk Carlton 1927 Sept 21, TMs (C), 27 p.
  - "A Real O. Henry Romance," by Paul Adams n.d., TMs, 4 p.
    An unpublished biographical account of Porter's "Texas days."
  - "The Return of the Songster," by William Sydney Porter n.d., TMs, 4 p.
  - "Schools and Schools," adapted for radio by Henry Fisk Carlton n.d., Near-Print, 29 p.
  - "The Scoop that Failed," by William Sydney Porter n.d., TMsS, 11 p.
  - "Some Pointers on Culture," by William Sydney Porter n.d., TMs, 2 p., 3 copies
  - "Tracked to Doom, or The Mystery of the Rue de Peychand," by William Sydney Porter [ca. 1894], TMs, includes two carbon copies, 2 p.
    A revised version appeared in an 1894 edition of the Rolling Stone.
  - "The Whirligigs of Life," adapted for radio by Henry Fisk Carlton n.d., TMs (C), 33 p.
  - "Whistling Sam's Christmas Stocking," by William Sydney Porter. [ca. 1989], TMs, 8 p. Includes two copies of a carbon excerpt from a revised version, 2 pages.
    Revised and published in 1899 as "Whistling Dick's Christmas Stocking."
  - An unidentifed excerpt, beginning "seemed so far removed from you," attributed to O. Henry n.d., TMs (C), 1 p., 2 copies
- Letters
  - William Sydney Porter to Stephen Fiske [1908?] Jul 16, TL, 1 p.
    In thanks for Fiske's favorable reviews of O. Henry's work
  - Stephen Fiske to (Doubleday and Company?) 1910 Oct 11, AN, 1 p.
    re Porter's letter of July 16 [1908?] and the article to which it refers
  - [Doubleday and Company?] to Stephen Fiske 1910 Oct 14, TL (C), 1 p.
    Concerning his note of Oct 11, 1910
  - Roy Mason to Mr. Doubleday, concerning his film adaptation of O. Henry's "Best Seller" 1925 Jun 21, ALS, 1 p.
  - [Doubleday?] to Roy Mason 1925 Jun 25, TL (C), 1 p.
    re payment for Mason's film adaptation of O. Henry's "Best Seller"
  - Kate Steichen to "all editors" 1958 Jun 20, TL, 15 p.
    re Doubleday and Company's collection of O. Henry manuscripts, including a chronological bibliography of William Sydney Porter's work
- Drawings
  - Pen-and-ink drawing of a cowboy in a city street, with a hand-lettered limerick, by William Sydney Porter n.d., Drawing
- Printed Material
  - "Proof of the Pudding," by O. Henry, from Broadway Magazine1907 May, Printed, 4 p.
  - "Rus in Urbe," by O. Henry, from Hampton's Magazine1909 Aug, Printed, 4 p.
  - "A Municipal Report," by O. Henry 1909 Nov, Printed, 5 p.
    Includes eight copies from Hampton's Magazine
  - "O. Henry's Most Humorous Letter" 1918 Sep 29, Broadside, 1 p.
    Publication of a letter written in 1905 by Sydney Porter to Mr. George Rathborne to apologize for his unintentional use of Rathborne's name in a short story, "Tommy's Burglar," which was later published in Whirligigs